A Guide to the Papers of the Twyman Family
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Twyman Family 1835-1865
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11549
ca. 190 items
The papers consist of correspondence of the Twyman family with friends and relatives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift from Mrs. E. C. Eisenhardt, Charlottesville, Va., September 1, 1999.
Scope and Content Information
The papers consist of correspondence of the Twyman family with friends and relatives. The papers include letters, 1861-1865, from Walker G. Twyman, with the 19th Virginia Infantry, describing battles, marches and conditions in Virginia camps and Chimborazo Hospital, Richmond, Virginia. Specific Civil War topics include Charlottesville troops at Harper's Ferry; Camp Pickens; battle at Fairfax Court House; execution of spies; 1st Manassas; rumors, picket duty; Seven Days' Battles; prisoners dying of typhoid at Chimborazo; sending of food and supplies to soldiers; and fighting at Gordonsville. Other topics include the settlement of an estate in Albemarle County, Va.; a Virginia Central Railroad Company Report on inability to pay a divident; a baptism in an Earlysville Baptist church; an ailing child with "curved spine"; the sale of a slave in poor health; and bail for Charles [Watts ?] in Lexington, Ky.
Contents List
- Letters of Garret Watts (Husband of Martha Twyman Watts--daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Twyman) 1837-1855 (Box 1)
  Arranged chronologically
  - Lexington, Ky. -- to Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Twyman (in-laws) at Longwood P.O., Albemarle County June 28, 1837 (Box 1)
    mentions problem concerning raising bail to release Charles from jail and have him move immediately to Kentucky from Virginia-fears Charles life may be in danger; mentions marriage of Lucy Watts to Walter G. Ferguson, a grandson of Walter Carr, formerly of Albemarle County.
  - Lexington, Ky --to in-laws in Albemarle County July 29, 1838 (Box 1)
    --concerning illness of son William who is being treated for "curved spine;" talks of details of will of $20,000 to $30,000 he is handling for deceased husband of Mrs.[Beverly] Broadus.
  - Lexington, Ky.--to in-laws in Albemarle County June 30, 1839 (Box 1)
    William still ill and not expected to recover; tells specifics of sale of Albert, a slave, for $700; Albert's poor health lowered his selling price, but he was sold without "warranty" so "if he should become worse and die the purchaser can not come back on me"; has received a letter from Charles indicating he has arrived at his home safely.
  - Lexington, Ky.-- to parents in Albemarle County from daughter, Martha Twyman Watts Sep 29, 1839 (Box 1)
    William worsening; Lucy Ferguson and husband living at their home
  - from Fayette City, Ky. To Joseph W. Twyman, Earlysville,Va. Jan 10-19, 1851 (Box 1)
    Two letters concerning will executions
  - from Fayette City, Ky.-to Joseph W.. Twyman Apr 27 1851 (Box 1)
  - from Fayette City, Ky. --to Joseph W. Twyman, Earlysville, Va. Oct 7, 1851 (Box 1)
    wants Twyman to fix date in November for settlement of his father's estate.
- Civil War Letters of Walker G. Twyman (Sergeant--Co. B--19th Regiment Virginia Volunteers) Feb 2 1858 (Box 1)
  - Charlottesville to brother Billy (William R. Twyman ) Feb 2 1858, Folder 1858-1859 (Box 1)
    Charlottesville to brother Billy (William R. Twyman)
  - Charlottesville to sister Sallie Oct 25 1859, Folder 1858-1859 (Box 1)
    describing a baptizing in a Baptist church in Earlysville
  - Charlottesville to sister Sallie Dec 20 1859, Folder 1858-1859 (Box 1)
    mentions that everyone is full of "military spirit" and that he has joined a new company - all rifle
  - Harper's Ferry to Billy Feb 26 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-Jun (Box 1)
    full of interesting details about troop trip from Charlottesville via Gordonsville to Harper's Ferry, where Federals had just left having not heard of the passing of the ordinance of Secession - describes train of powder left by Union forces which was ignited, blowing up buildings containing arms; describes hearing rumors that Lincoln had left Washington; gives troop numbers at Harper's Ferry; tells of the troops walking from Strasburg to Winchester and the ills they suffered; tells of the hoisting of the southern flag over Harper's Ferry; mentions being at Martinsburg where more southern troops are expected and writes of the crowded conditions there; includes a hand drawn map of positions of forces on various hills at Harper's Ferry.
  - Camp Henry near Culpeper Court House to brother Billy May 17 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-Jun (Box 1)
    - talks of meeting friends from Greene County, John Williams and John Eddins; reports a great many ladies are about catching the soldiers' eyes.
  - Camp Pickens, Manassas Station May 26 1861 through June 4 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    This is a combination report and letter to brother Billy which covers three long pages of paper from an old accounting book with an insert letter. On May 27, he notes that there has been a false report that the enemy was within one mile of camp; on May 28, he writes that General Lee has arrived at camp from Richmond, that the Carolina regiment has encamped 8 miles away at Centreville, that one spy of the enemy has been shot and two more taken prisoners; on May 29, 200 troops from Goochland have arrived, hears that England has recognized the Confederacy; on May 30, drill times have changed, General Lee starts back to Richmond, Tom [Parish] arrives from Harper's Ferry with dispatch for General Lee, General Milledge Luke Bonham addresses troops, another spy is shot; on May 31, more troops are gathering below Fort Henry; on June 1, 450 soldiers arrive at daybreak, General Beauregard (Pierre Gustave Toutant) and General Lee come from Richmond, hears that President Jefferson Davis arrived in Richmond May 28, describes in detail battle that morning at Fairfax Court House, two companies of the first regiment of Virginia were involved, 50 of the Confederate riflemen drove back 80 federal troops, the captain of his rifle company was killed with a shot through the heart. On June 2, describes capture of more prisoners; on June 4, more prisoners taken, troops from Georgia pass through on way to Harper's Ferry; on June [5] goes to Bull Run to begin digging entrenchments. The insert letter to brother Billy on May 31 tells of a spy captured by the South Carolina regiment who had a map of encampments. He was convicted and shot.
  - Manassas Station to brother Billy June 1 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    tells of Generals Beauregard and Lee arriving from Richmond; repeats details of battle that A.M. at Fairfax Court House, and describes throwing up breastworks about his camp.
  - Manassas Station to brother Billy June 3 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    notes movements of four companies of the first regiment of Virginia companies with two or three cavalry companies moving toward Fairfax Court House; still building breastworks.
  - Manassas Station to brother Billy June 5 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    (written on freight way bill of the Virginia Central Railroad) - "sending my jug - keep it until I send word to send it"; writes that they have received word to pack baggage.
  - Camp Pickens, Manassas Station to brother Billy June 5 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    hard rain; expect to move tents "tomorrow" about four miles below present site "here on Bull Run" to nearer the railroad.
  - advanced picket-Camp Pickens, stationed on Bull Run June 15 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    describes being at the post since "a week ago yesterday," and his picket duty, which has been steady; some men ill; a regiment has arrived and camped one mile below on the Run; some soldiers still arriving from Harper's Ferry and other points; tells of staying up all night while on duty and listening to sounds of bull frogs, crickets and "even an owl hoot."
  - advanced picket-Camp Pickens, stationed on Bull Run June 16 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    another regiment arrives and stops near his camp; another goes to Charlottesville.
  - Camp Pickens to Billy June 19 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    soldiers still arriving; "our soldiers are progressing by degrees toward Alexandria; tells of small fight at Vienna on the Louden & Hamshire Railroad --seven Yankees killed, took forty guns and some provisions.
  - Bull Run to Billy June 20 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    - learns that 30 of C.S.A. men with small cannon fired on one regiment of [Bellengers] Yankees on train going up the railroad; gives account of supposed number killed at possibly 200
  - Bull Run to Billy June 21 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    hears that his regiment may leave in the morning for Romney
  - Camp Pickens to Billy n.d., Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    thinks 8,000 troops are in the vicinity - sent a box with vest, coat and jug "with money to get the best whisky and send it down by the first chance."
  - Centreville to Billy June 23 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    arrived yesterday in Centerville where a whole regiment from Albemarle is present; located five miles from the camp on Bull Run; asks that Billy send the whisky and keep his letters
  - Centreville to Billy June 29 1861, Folder 1861 Jan-June (Box 1)
    describes Centerville and "houses built before Braddock's defeat;" reflects on movements thus far --"one week on trip to Harper's Ferry; two weeks at Charlottesville; two weeks at Culpeper Court House; two weeks at Manassas Junction, and two weeks at Bull Run; gives an account of his reactions to each place; says troops are drilling hard and that there are eight roads leading from present position; false alarm in camp last night when "some of the fellows were scared out of their senses."
  - Centreville to Billy July 4 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    request for shirt and discussion of clothing needs
  - Centreville to Billy July 4 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    remarks that the accounting book paper he is writing on should last for some time
  - Centreville to Billy July 5-9 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    three notes with matters pertaining to requests for food and clothing
  - Centreville to Billy July 12 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    has been in camp three months; describes daily routine
  - Centreville to Miss Milly July 12 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    long letter describing his troop movements and attributes not writing to being pestered by people while on picket duty; tells of recreational activities
  - Centreville to Billy July 17 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    this letter is a report of daily activities through July 23--July 17, struck tents and retreated to Bull Run; July 18, fight at Mitchell's field--enemy routed; July 21, general fight with first fire opened on Latham's battery at Lewis Ford--describes fight; July 22, collecting plunder that enemy scattered; July 23, advanced almost to Centreville, describes skirmishing there--"the firing was equal to the panorama of the Russian War"
  - Bull Run, copy of a news clipping of "Brilliant Victory Near Manassas" from the Jeffersonian newspaper of Charlottesville July 19 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
  - Bull Run to Billy July 22 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    raining; took about 30 cannon yesterday--18 or 20 rifled canon; "I recon more men engaged in the fight than in the history of the U.S."
  - Camp near Centreville to Sallie July 29 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    extract from Mrs. [Hemans] Works, a long poem which "I altered to fit the times"
  - Near Centreville to Billy Aug 2 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    wants bread, soda and coffee; describes his cooking efforts
  - Manassas Junction to Billy Aug 3 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    tells of burying the dead, sending Yankee wounded (those well enough to move) to Richmond. Yankees are being buried by Confederates--thinks about 3000 Yankees killed and wounded--600 C.S.A. killed
  - Near Centreville to Billy Aug 10 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    has been ill and taking laudanum; received orders in the morning to be ready for marching
  - Centreville to Billy Aug 16 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    describes the difference between "standing still to be shot at and not shoot, and rushing up in the fight." He writes: "When the Yankees fired at us, and Latham fired at them, it was as much as the captains could do to keep the men from firing at the Yankee skirmishers. There were 10,000 Yankees in front of us and we kept them back without firing a musket except the cannon which killed 200 if not more."
  - Centreville to Billy Aug 21 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    everything quiet with regards to fighting
  - Centreville to Billy Aug 22 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    after retreat of Yankees, [Burnie] Brown's company went on the battlefield and got as much plunder as they could carry--"it shows what they are--they didn't take any part in the fight at all."
  - Centreville to Billy Aug 26-27 1861, Folder 1861 Jul-Aug (Box 1)
    orders to get ready to advance have been rescinded
  - Fairfax Court House to Billy Sept 1 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    preparing for picket duty at a hill close to Falls Church, which C.S.A. took possession of last week
  - Fairfax Court House to Billy Sept 3 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    reports that when he moved from Centreville he lost all his clothes except those he had on; describes picket duty on Munson's Hill where there is scavenging for corn and potatoes to eat; lines of C.S.A. and Union pickets are 300 to 500 yards from each other--firing all the time--"I could see Yankees very plain." Location is six miles from Alexandria and D.C.
  - Fairfax Court House to Billy Sept 13 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    wants to hire a "free" boy to cook for him and asks Billy to find one as "cheap as you can."
  - Fairfax Court House to Billy Sept 15 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    going on picket duty again at Mason's Hill--more fighting about four miles this side of Washington
  - Fairfax Court House to Billy Sept 24 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    "I would not mind being in camp if it was not a complete waste of time."
  - Two miles from Annandale to ? Sept 29 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    came there with a Kentucky regiment the day before--drove back some Yankees
  - On picket duty, to Sister Sallie Sept 30-Oct 1 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    G. Watson Carr is now Lt. Col. (Acting Col.) of the regiment instead of Col. Strange, who is acting commander of the right in Richmond
  - Fairfax County Court House Oct 1-8 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    on guard at Beauregard headquarters
  - Fairfax County Court House Oct 6 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    wants sweet potatoes, chestnuts, and butter sent to him
  - Fairfax County Court House, to friends and fellow citizens Oct 9-15 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    describes escaping being hit by a ball and a small fight at Stone bridge between two Yank companies and his picket
  - Camp near Centreville to Billy Oct 15-17 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Aug (Box 1)
    tells of march to 1 mile south of Centreville where the whole force has fallen back
  - Camp near Centreville to Billy Oct 19-27 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
  - Camp near Centreville to Sallie Oct 31 1861, Folder 1861 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
    writes about his army life and how he has adapted to it
  - Camp near Centreville to Billy Nov 6 1861, Folder 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 1)
    describes three ladies passing by which caused the band to come out to play for them
  - Camp near Centreville to Billy Nov 17 1861, Folder 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 1)
    reports on the building of chimneys on the tents to make them comfortable
  - Camp near Centreville to Billy and Sallie Nov 19-Dec 2 1861, Folder 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 1)
    several letters with minutiae
  - Camp near Centreville to Billy Dec 6 1861, Folder 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 1)
    describes a 14' by 16' house they are building which ten soldiers will live in
  - Camp near Centreville to Bill Dec 14 1861, Folder 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 1)
    picket post has been changed
  - Camp near Centreville to Sallie Dec 15 1861, Folder 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 1)
    writes about life in the camp, with a description of some ladies who were visiting
  - Camp near Centreville to Bill Dec 26 1861, Folder 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 1)
    plenty of good food as a result of Christmas gifts
  - Camp near Centreville to Bill Dec 31 1861, Folder 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 1)
    reports that he has heard Brig. Gen. [Philip St. George] Cocke has shot himself with a pistol--the "ball entering his head near one ear and coming out the other ear"
  - Camp near Centreville to Bill Jan 20 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    wants Bill to hire him another cook
  - Camp near Centreville to Bill Feb 11 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    many volunteers reenlisting
  - Camp near Centreville to Bill Feb 15 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    snowing, hears heavy firing on the Potomac
  - Chimborazo Hospital, Richmond to Bill Mar 7 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    "I was taken with mumps last Monday, sent to the hospital at Manassas on Wednesday and started to Richmond yesterday morning--got here last night. If the cars down had not been locked when I got to Gordonsville, I would have gotten out and come to Charlottesville."
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Bill Mar 7 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    asks Bill to see Dr. Cabell in Charlottesville and see if he can get him transferred there from Chimborazo Hospital
  - Richmond City to Bill Mar 11 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    is better, still awaiting reply from Dr. Cabell; expects to get a situation at the hospital as an assistant steward under William B. Ward in No. 4 at $30 per month
  - to Sergt. W.G. Twyman from Dr. J.L. Cabell, General Hospital, Charlottesville Mar 13 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    understands Twyman's request for a transfer but recommends that he write himself to the surgeon-general making this request
  - copy of official permission of the CSA War Department for W.G. Twyman to visit Albemarle County April 9 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Pa and Ma April 16 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    describes troop movements through Richmond for Yorktown
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Bill April 27 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    hears hospital may be moved to Danville; has been assigned to the clerk's office in division No. 5
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Bill May 9 1862, Folder 1862 Jan-May (Box 1)
    hears many reports circulating about killed, wounded and missing in the 19th Va.; excitement in Richmond very great.
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Sallie June 4 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
    describes fighting around Richmond and the hard work of women of the city who are caring for the wounded
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Billy June 5 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
    gives advice on joining the service
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Bill and all July 2-3 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Billy July 7 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
    prisoners being brought in every day and many of the sick are dying with typhoid fever
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Sallie and Bill July 9 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
    (written on "Confederate" paper) weather very hot; patients dying fast
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Sallie July 15 1862, Folder 1862 Jul-Oct (Box 1)
    tells of visit to Richmond where cost of food is exorbitant; reports that in month of June, mortality rate at the hospital was 350; about 3000 patients in the hospital
  - Chimborazo Hospital to Bill Aug 3 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
    many wounded gone on furlough; reports return of extreme pain in his side
  - From Chimborazo Hospital to Walker Sep 3 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
    letter from R.M. Stephens, friend, about fellow soldiers at Chimborazo
  - From ? to Bill Sep 8 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
    tells of "Spooner" leaving his coat with William B. Ward and says he will seee about it as soon as he gets back to the hospital. "I can not get out of the house."
  - From ? to Daddy Sep 23, 1862, Folder 1862 June-Oct (Box 1)
    reports on encounter between Jackson and Burnside near the Potomac in which Burnside was solidly beaten.
- Letters of William R. Twyman 1856-1864 (Box 1)
  - from father in Charlottesville Jan 10 1856 (Box 1)
  - from nephew in Iowa Mar 4 1859 (Box 1)
  - to father Oct 12 1861 (Box 1)
  - newspaper report from William of death in Albemarle County of John C. Wilhoit Aug 25 1862 (Box 1)
  - to father Jan 12 1862 (Box 1)
  - to father Jan 25 1862 (Box 1)
  - from Charlottesville to father Mar ? 1862 (Box 1)
    says he will write to surgeon general asking for transfer of Walker Twyman to hospital in Charlottesville
  - to father from Charlottesville July 15 1862 (Box 1)
    hears that Walker is thin but mending
  - to father July 23 1862 (Box 1)
  - to mother from Charlottesville Jan 12 1864 (Box 1)
  - several news items May 8 1864 (Box 1)
    hard fighting around Gordonsville, with General Ewell taking 6,000 enemy prisoners and thousands of enemy dead upon the fields; reports that enemy has attacked Beauregard's lines below City of Richmond
  - to father from Charlottesville Dec 1 1864 (Box 1)
    discusses law passed by Congress concerning tax certificate
  - four letters to father n.d. (Box 1)
- Letters to Joseph W. Twyman 1840-1875 (Box 1)
  - Lexington, Ky. from M.G. Johnson Dec 23, 1840 (Box 1)
    details of a suit in General Court against Richard Broadus and Beverly Broadus [Hiss] on a Judgment and Injunction bond in favor of George Twyman's executors
  - Richmond, from G.H. Gilmer Mar 15 1840 (Box 1)
    business matters
  - Shelby County, Ky., from John Younger Feb 25 1843 (Box 1)
    provides names of heirs of Agatha Deening for purpose of distributing assets of will of George Twyman
  - Richmond, from J.A. Weed Mar 13 1843 (Box 1)
    details concerning claim to a tract of land in Albemarle County estate of R.H. Johnston, of which Twyman is executor (includes drawn map of tract)
  - Shelbyville, Ky., from James Twyman, Jr. Mar 13 1843 (Box 1)
    more requests concerning adequate and proper execution of assets of his grandfather's estates
  - Shelbyville, Ky. from James Twyman, Jr. July 24 1843 (Box 1)
    requests response to earlier letter about settlement of grandfather's estate
  - One share in Virginia Central Railroad Company in the name of Joseph W. Twyman Sept 12 1850 (Box 1)
  - soil sample request April 3 1851 (Box 1)
  - Chimborazo Hospital Richmond, from M.M. [Kennel] Oct 30 1862 (Box 1)
    concerning the collection of back pay for Walker Twyman (now deceased)
  - Office of Viginia Central Railroad Co. Feb 4 1867 (Box 1)
    report on inability to pay dividend
  - Virginia Central Railroad Company payment of dividend Dec 13 1867 (Box 1)